NAMRTA SHARMA

18790, Lloyd Drive, Apt#238, Dallas 75252, Texas nxs200001@utdallas.edu, namrta@yahoo.com (+1) 9089437244

SUMMARY

Highly motivated, industrious, bilingual female public service professional from India pursuing Ph.D. in Public Affairs at University of Texas at Dallas. Background includes a vast and varied experience in the field of Human Resource Management while working in various management positions in the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), Ministry of Agriculture, Government of India.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), May 1995 – July 2021 Ministry of Agriculture, Govt. of India

Positions held:

Director (Administration) (November, 2020 to July 2021)

Human Resource Management functions including outsourcing; Arranging for the highest decision-making bodies viz. Governing Body and Annual General Body Meetings.

Deputy Secretary-Agricultural Extension (June 2018- Nov 2020)

Budget planning, release of finance and expenditure monitoring for the world's largest agricultural extension network; Coordinating with Central/State Govts/other national and international agencies for implementation of various other outreach programs for the farmers.

Deputy Secretary -Administration & Personnel (April 2012 - June 2015)

Human Resource Management functions; Implementation of the e-governance initiatives at a national level (more than 100 locations

Deputy Secretary-Crop Science (June 2015 - Dec 2015)

Processed all type of issues at the central level for Research Institutes involved land transfers, construction of building, provisioning of staff, budgeting and fund allocation in various heads annually, monitoring of expenditure etc.

Deputy Secretary/Under Secretary-Recruitment at Agricultural Scientists' Recruitment Board (April 2004-March 2012)

Recruiting functions at national level of very senior scientific positions including advertising open positions; Holding of national level examinations for filling up vacant positions; Policy initiatives for improvement in recruitment functions.

Senior Administrative Officer, National Bureau of Plant Genetic Resources (May2003 to April 2004)

Financial and administrative management of the organization; Liaison with other government Departments and local civic bodies for issues like property tax, building plan; Addressing audit para, grievances, queries, legal matters.

Registrar (Academic), Indian Agricultural Research Institute, Deemed University May 1995 – April 2003

Overall administrative and academic management of the top Agricultural university in India having 600 national and international graduate (Masters and PhD) students; Student/ Faculty information management; Arrangements relating to Annual Convocation.

EDUCATION

Management Development Institute, Gurugram, Haryana- India

21 months Post Graduate Diploma in Public Policy and Management sponsored by Govt of India Including one semester at George Mason University, Washington D.C., 2007

University of Delhi, New Delhi-India

Master of Science in Physics, 1993 Bachelor of Science (Hons.) in Physics, 1991

AWARDS/FELLOWSHIPS

- 1. Junior Research Fellowship in Physics, 1993.
- 2. National Eligibility Test for Lecturer ship in Physics, 1993.

SKILLS

- Fluent in Hindi and English.
- Knowledge of programming in Python and C.
- GRE- 312; TOEFL-99

DISSERTATIONS/PUBLICATIONS

- A comparative study of organization design of the public and private (both profit and nonprofit) agricultural research organizations in India-Dissertation for completion of the requirements of the Postgraduate Diploma in Public Policy and Management (2008)
- Edited book named 'Dr. B. P. Pal and his Roses'.

ARTICLE REVIEWS

• Peer reviewed "Life Under COVID-19 Restrictions: Qualitative Study of livelihood and Social implications on *Gulit*¹ seller women in Dässé Town in the Amhara Region,

¹ A *gulït* is an open-air marketplaces where people can stay and carry out their trading activities are typically poorly designed and often informal poorly designed and often informal.

- Ethiopia, the Case of Robït *Gulït* Sellers'; International Journal of Sociology and Anthropology (IJSA)(2022)
- Peer review Agri-Business Incubator: RKVY RAFTAAR R-ABI, NAIF-ABI, by Mallikarjunaiah SN; Academia Letters (2022)

TALKS / MEMBERSHIPS

- Chairperson of Promotion Committees in ICAR
- Member, Budget Planning Committee, ICAR
- Invited Expert, Selection Committee, Administrative Officer, Indian institute of Food Processing Technology, India (2017,2019)
- Invited Speaker, International Women's Day program, 2016,2020,2021
- Invited Speaker, Foundation Course for Agricultural Scientists (2017)
- Member, Selection Committee, Social Media professional, ICAR
- Coordinator, Foundation Day lecture series (2009,2010,2011) of Agricultural Scientists Recruitment Board, India